XINLEI DENG

SUMMARY

I am a Ph.D. Candidate in Department of Environmental Health Sciences, University at Albany, State University of New York, advised by Prof. Shao Lin. My research interest focuses on the application of remote sensing techniques, geospatial analysis, and machine learning methods in public health. For Implementation Sciences, I prefer building online predictive models for practical application. I worked as research project assistant with 3 years of experience offering statistical analysis and expertise in various study design including cohort, case control, case crossover, and time series. My Ph.D. thesis is to assess the short-term association between meteorological factors and emergency department visits for mental disorders by using high-resolution weather simulations. I obtained my bachelor's degree in public health and medicine in Sun Yat-sen University in 2019. My thesis entitled "Time series clustering analysis on the epidemiological characteristics of notifiable infectious diseases in China" was awarded the Outstanding Thesis. I have a strong background in medicine, biostatistics, epidemiology.

EXPERIENCE

Research Project Assistant, 07/2019 - Current

The Research Foundation of State University of New York- Albany, NY

- Worked as **project coordinator** for several grants.
- Used advanced analytical approaches including machine learning models to evaluate health risk factors.
- Develop spatial modeling with R, Python and ArcGIS.
- Built predictive models and deployed them as web-based tools.
- Manage big electronic hospital data with SAS
- Applied Coxph, DLNM and case crossover design to solving problems in public health and clinical research.

Teaching Assistant, 05/2021 - 08/2021

The Research Foundation of State University of New York- Albany, NY

- Provided one-on-one assistance and tutoring to clinicians requiring additional help.
- Helped clinicians master learning concepts through one-on-one and small group tutoring.
- Helped professors with material generation, lesson plan development, class preparation, scheduling, exam distribution and student mentoring.

Biostatistics Scientist Intern, 01/2019 - 06/2019

Changsha Duxact Biotech Co., Ltd

- Drafted statistical sections of study protocols outlining information such as rationale, objectives, design and methodology.
- Prepared datasets using SAS.
- Prepared statistical analysis plan and report.

Data Management Intern, 02/2018 - 03/2018

Hunan BRI Medicine Co., Ltd. - Hunan



CONTACT

Address: Albany, NY 12203

Phone: 518-253-2901

Email: xdeng3@albany.edu

Website: https://xinleideng.github.io/

SKILLS

- Python, R, SAS, ArcGIS, SPSS, SQL, Photoshop, STATA, Matlab
- Developed online tools:

xdeng3.shinyapps.io/CHD_model/ xdeng3.shinyapps.io/COVID-19/

ACADEMIC SERVICES

- Served as reviewer for Indoor Air, Health and Place, & BioMed Research International journals.
- Served as moderator at the American Public Health Association (APHA) conference for Big Data Analytics for Public Health Research session 2021
- Served as The Nation's Health Board Representative (Chair) for APHA - Student Assembly 2021

HONORS

- George Scholarship 2021
- Registration award at 2021 ISEE conference
- Student and New Researcher Network (SNRN) Award at 2020 ISEE conference.
- The Health Research, Inc. David Axelrod Award 2020

- Detected and resolved data quality issues and discrepancies for integrity and quality control.
- Devised reports and visualizations to present requested data in sleek format.

Intern Doctor, 09/2017 - 01/2019

Kaiping Central Hospital - Kaiping

Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University - Guangzhou Sixth Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University - Guangzhou Hailong Street Community Healthcare Service Center - Guangzhou Yiyang Central Hospital - Hunan

- Recorded patients' medical history, vital statistics and test results in electronic medical records. Facilitated patient check-ins and check-outs.
- Prepared patients for specific treatments.
- Monitored patients with acute conditions for changes, improvements or need for intervention.

PUBLICATIONS

- Sheridan SC, Zhang W, **Deng X**, Lin S. The individual and synergistic impacts of windstorms and power outages on injury ED visits in New York State. Sci Total Environ. 2021;797:149199.
- Hu K, Deng X, et al. Development and validation of a predictive model for feeding
 intolerance in intensive care unit patients with sepsis. Saudi J Gastroenterol Off J
 Saudi Gastroenterol Assoc. Published online 2021.
- Zhang T, Zhang G, **Deng X**, et al. APS (Age, Platelets, 2D Shear-Wave Elastography) Score Predicts Hepatocellular Carcinoma in Chronic Hepatitis B. Radiology. Published online 2021:204700.
- Deng X, Zhang W, et al. Short-term risk effects of exposure to ultrafine particles on emergency department visits of renal diseases in New York State, 2013-2017.
 ISEE Conf Abstr. 2021;2021(1). doi:10.1289/ISEE.2021.O-TO-127
- Qu Y, Zhang W, Ryan I, **Deng X**, et al. Ambient extreme heat exposure in summer and transitional months and emergency department visits and hospital admissions due to pregnancy complications. Sci Total Environ. 2021;777:146134. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146134
- Lin S, **Deng X**, et al. COVID-19 Symptoms and Deaths Among Health Care Workers in the United States. Published online 2021.
- Deng X, Thurston G, Zhang W, et al. Application of data science methods to identify school and home risk factors for asthma and allergy-related symptoms among children in New York. Sci Total Environ. 2021;770. doi:10.1016/J.SCITOTENV.2020.144746
- Guo J, Wu Y, Deng X, et al. Association between social determinants of health and direct economic burden on middle-aged and elderly individuals living with diabetes in China. PLoS One. 2021;16(4):e0250200. doi:10.1371/JOURNAL.PONE.0250200
- Ye B, Zhang W, Deng X, et al. Impacts of environmental policies on students' test scores mediating by school attendance rate. ISEE Conf Abstr. 2020;2020(1). doi:10.1289/ISEE.2020.VIRTUAL.P-1249
- Deng X, Brotzge J, Zhang W, et al. Assessing the association between meteorological factors and mental disorders in summer using Mesonet, a refined weather monitoring system, in New York State. ISEE Conf Abstr. 2020;2020(1). doi:10.1289/ISEE.2020.VIRTUAL.P-0334
- **Deng X**, Zhang W, Lin S. Package 'APML.' https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/APML/APML.pdf. Published online 2020.

- Honorable Mention in American

 Mathematical Contest in Modeling 2018
- First prize at provincial level in China Undergraduate Mathematical Contest in Modeling 2017
- Outstanding Thesis Recipient in Sun Yat-sen University
- SYSU First Class Scholarship, SYSU Jerry Yan Scholarship, Scholarship of Zhibin Yao and Xiao Tan for Excellent Medical Students Recipient
- The Third Prize of the Sixth Medical Knowledge & Skills Contests

EDUCATION & TRAINING

Bachelor of Science in Medicine, Public Health, 06/2019

Sun Yat-sen Univeristy - Guangzhou, China

- Thesis: Time series clustering analysis on the epidemiological characteristics of notifiable infectious diseases in China
- 3.8/4 GPA

Ph.D., Environmental Health Sciences, Expected in 12/2022

SUNY At Albany - Albany, NY

- Full scholarship Recipient
- Travel award for conference
- 4.97/5 GPA

Certificate in Biostatistics, 08/2020

Peking University - Beijing, China

 Training in deep learning, adaptive design, dynamic treatment regime, missing imputation, stochastic epidemic model, and longitudinal data analysis.

- Cai Y, Gong W, He H, Hughes J, Simoni J, Xiao S, Gloyd S, Lin M, Deng X, et al. Mobile texting and lay health supporters to improve schizophrenia care in a resource-poor community in rural China (LEAN Trial): Randomized controlled trial extended implementation. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22(12). doi:10.2196/22631
- Wang T, Xu D, Fan Q, Rong W, Zheng J, Gao C, Li G, Zeng N, Guo T, Zeng L, Wang F, Xiao C, Cai L, Tang S, **Deng X**, et al. 1,2-Dichloroethane impairs glucose and lipid homeostasis in the livers of NIH Swiss mice. Toxicology. 2017;380:38-49. doi:10.1016/J.TOX.2017.02.005